<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Alegarciy's Blog</title><link>//localhost:1313/</link><description>Recent content on Alegarciy's Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:54:49 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>FastAPI Background</title><link>//localhost:1313/Posts/fast-api-sebastian-ramirez-interview/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>//localhost:1313/Posts/fast-api-sebastian-ramirez-interview/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="sebastian-ramirez---the-creator-of-fastapi">
 Sebastian Ramirez - the creator of FastAPI
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#sebastian-ramirez---the-creator-of-fastapi">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="motives">
 Motives
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#motives">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This week at work we were planning to create a feature for a Python API for our event ingestions from different micro-service architecture. Given the option there was an idea to develop the back-end in Flask or other frameworks but a new framework was suggested that is called FastAPI. Then for some reason, the lead of the team proposed the migration without considering before the option (that is really bad) and a new member suggested we try out the FastAPI alternative because is more maintained at the moment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My Zettlekasten</title><link>//localhost:1313/Posts/starting-zettlekasten-note-system/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>//localhost:1313/Posts/starting-zettlekasten-note-system/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="zettlekastens-note-taking-system-first-approach-and-review">
 Zettlekastens note taking system: First approach and review.
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#zettlekastens-note-taking-system-first-approach-and-review">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="how-the-idea-of-note-taking-was-conceived">
 How the idea of note taking was conceived
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#how-the-idea-of-note-taking-was-conceived">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At first, I started taking notes on paper since 2023 in an informal manner. I noticed that I became dependent on them, more so than I expected at first always searching for notes i didn&amp;rsquo;t record and learnings I must have forgotten because of my long-term retention capacity. Finally this year (2024), I decided to commit myself to have a formal approach on note taking.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Start of a journey</title><link>//localhost:1313/Posts/blog/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>//localhost:1313/Posts/blog/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="first-blog-experience">
 First blog experience
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#first-blog-experience">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I think that sharing knowledge is something I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to do, no matter if its with my school friends, at work or on the internet through forums and disguise as another funny looking profile with a funny sounding name. I think that everyone is a bucket full of ideas waiting to be spilled and enjoyed by others like myself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I would like to dedicate this block to all those good ideas that I need to share, and for those who were around and manage to inspire me, for non of them are only mine.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title/><link>//localhost:1313/Posts/github-profile/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>//localhost:1313/Posts/github-profile/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="github-profile">
 Github Profile
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#github-profile">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="motives">
 Motives
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#motives">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I want to be able to make my Github page profile better looking, have a nice feel when people investigate my profile and projects. I want it to feel elegant and minimalistic, without too much overhead you have to go through. I watched a couple of profiles that implemented this ideas and I liked the approach enough to wanting to do it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references--observations">
 References &amp;amp;&amp;amp; Observations
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#references--observations">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Languages and Tools Section because of Dropdown is cool. &lt;a href="https://github.com/gautamkrishnar/gautamkrishnar">Profile Gautamkrishnar&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="project-development">
 Project Development
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#project-development">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is a project that won&amp;rsquo;t take more than 2 weeks, so the t-shirt size i would say feels like a XS. I notice that the Readme.md files could be scripted and filled with information on them by creating cron jobs of actions or even trigger actions inside Github. That means there is a lot of programmability you can add to your profile, that will extend the profile view form a basic markup project to a bigger project to showcase your creativity. (This was discovered specifically in the Simon Willison&amp;rsquo;s article).&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>